all right welcome everyone to another
awakening from the meaning crisis disk
or QA our guest today is Tim Ottawa or
how do you pronounce your name your last
name Tim Adeline Adeline thanks Adeline
Adalia thanks for being here Tim thank
you for inviting me
yeah so so Tim is a philosopher
interested in the art of transformation
he's the owner of the voice craft
collective website and podcast so Tim so
you actually joined reform a little
while ago and thank you for that what
maybe you could tell us a little bit
about yourself and your background and
you know what's brought you into this
whole sphere of the the internet that we
find ourselves in yeah sure thank you I
mean definitely feeling that energy as
well I'm just smiling yeah well look I
mean I think possibly like most everyone
here I'm here because I was following
questions and an embodied sense and need
ultimately for meaning in life to do
something with it that was valuable to
make sense of it in a way that afforded
me to do meaningful and valuable things
and fundamentally that seems to be
nested in a sense of love which is
somehow an ask and on asking I haven't
used those words before to describe it
but things seem to ground out in just a
fundamental affirmation of being and
then you sort of have to work up like
what the we are doing here like can
we do things that are helpful or not and
that journey goes back a long way so you
know like everyone begins begins while
in the womb fundamentally you can speak
about it from like a stanislav grof
perspective which i think is quite
interesting the perinatal matrices of
these stages of the birthing process
which have arguable effects on the
dynamics of the psyche as it unfolds
throughout life but we're all used to
talking about things and sort of
developmental terms like how we were
when we were children what opportunities
were afforded to
what kind of traumas we experienced what
things we were able to learn and how we
came to mature and so the story begins
there for me but skipping a whole way
down look I mean John vivec II his work
I think is fantastic and his pedagogy is
as good as his work which is also
fantastic and it was someone whose ideas
I came into contact with in around 2014
2015 and I found that it was a bit of a
refuge point or at least knowing that
there was a not that I was looking for
scientific explanations and of course
there are limits to what John is really
even looking for science to achieve
regarding at least relevance obviously
he thinks we can have a science of
relevance realization but it was it was
like a bit of a lighthouse for me in the
world of institution because I never
really found any professor in my years
of studying at different universities so
I did a Bachelor in philosophy in
international relations and a master's
in philosophy which I almost failed and
you know took many years to complete
because I was pursuing independent
research that was basically stemming
from an interest in psychedelics and a
dissatisfaction with the state of
philosophy of mind so taking a hard
problem very seriously but feeling that
from within analytic philosophy
essentially everyone is basically in
equipped to actually integrate the
quality of consciousness with Theory
building there's something to
disembodied about the whole project and
doesn't make appropriate doesn't come
into appropriate relationship with the
mystical to say nothing and to say
little let's say nothing of that I mean
people are still hung up on the quality
of the color red you know obviously that
they're looking for that as an example
of qualia just kind of like a base feel
of consciousness and what it is to be
liked but I wish is felt man there's
this what it is to be is to be in
enmeshed
in in continued quality and and I just
felt that in sort of in keeping with the
breakdown of teacherly Authority in
institutions writ large in keeping with
the kind of senescence and inadequacy of
our institutions writ large and our
perhaps our culture writ large elements
of it you know not meaning to be flippin
about that I felt as though the only way
I could ever kind of have the
conversations I wanted to have and the
only way I could feel to contribute in a
way that felt appropriate was to undergo
some process of creating a table even as
I spoke at it so this wasn't really a
place to to be to have the kind of
conversations I wanted to have now I
said you know John's work was kind of
like a lighthouse and it was one of the
few places it was but you know I'm not
from Canada and my life didn't quite
take those turns so as far as the
podcast goes you know that's been a
journey of three three and a half years
a bit longer and it is has been an
attempt really from the beginning to
have the kind of conversations that now
I referred to as the kind of deal logos
conversations I'm still a bit sort of
hesitant about using that language
myself because I think it has sort of
sacred connotations and also you know
it's been largely wouldn't it wouldn't
say it's been defined precisely but it's
being discussed and enacted in
environments that I'm often not a part
of and so I feel like well to say I'm
doing that thing might be not that
helpful in some sense but fundamentally
it has a placeholder term it seems like
that's kind of what it's about so here
we are you know I'm just keen to have a
chat with you guys and whether this is a
Q&A or just an opportunity for us all to
talk together you know I'm equally
interested so it's really nice to be
here with you thank you for inviting me
we're so happy to have you so so you
said a lot there you know as your
philosopher
throughout three words you know simple
words are not so simple and and get your
take on them and and these are words
that you've said just now and that we
speak a lot of but these words are
meaning love and sacred how how do you
frame those those words what is meaning
mean to you it's interesting when isn't
it because I think we probably all use
that word to me like ten hundred million
different things so it often kind of
depends what mode of communication I'm
engaging in I communicate to myself
quite differently when I'm writing and
that's mainly to myself it's not
designed always to be that way but I
find that the expression that comes out
when I'm trying to be absolutely clear
with language is not that exceptionally
translatable to speaking would sound
disjointed and technical but what would
I mean I would mean something meaning as
in one sense you can I take it at least
as kind of a a term that gestures or
references at the a a kind of nebulous
affectation a quality type dynamic which
is inherently a relational so I want to
say some process as I wanna say unit
like little thing but if it it's not a
thing it's a dynamic relation so in the
sense of John talking about the trans
Jack tivity and meaning being a sort of
a dynamical relation sort of realized
through a reciprocal relationship
between agent and arena so it's a kind
of it's a kind of fluid coupling
effectivity it exists in this trans Jace
it's a duration that we participate in
so like what so I mean in philosophy
people talk about intentionality there's
the discourse of our intentionality in
the philosophy of mind which is how do
our words or how do our gestures or how
do our science come to have kind
of how do they map onto things how do we
actually map onto the world what what do
our words what gives them the quality of
their meaning how do we get to actually
pick something out and so it's it's
partly something like that as well like
what enables us to differentiate between
what are many many meanings or so much
information
I mean spoken about kind of in that way
it's almost a bit amorphous right it's
kind of like everything's meaning but
then we differentiate and there's
perhaps a hierarchy of meaning that
maybe that's not the right word to use
we realize some meanings as more
relevant than others and undergoing
these processes like for John obviously
backed on underground like the
underground of it is that relevance
realization up and down the stack of
different kinds of knowing and
perception we come to differentiate and
integrate and all together build a world
and enact ourselves in a world that is
coherent or more or less coherent so the
meanings form some kind of picture or
perhaps story but not just a story it's
got its you know it depends what you
mean by story but it's the kind of
constituent elements of what enables
really things to make sense to us
something like that that's not really
much of a definition definition is it
but it's so it's so like images that
come to mind as far as sacred and love I
mean I I I do tend to think that Forrest
Landry's phrase love is that which
enables choice is a really beautiful non
lossless compression of some deeply
important notions so love being for me
love is something which both enables our
appropriate attachment and appropriate
detachment so love is something that can
let go as well as be in intimate
proximal touch with which is a quite
remarkable thing that we can both love
something and let it go so there's an
enabling there love is something that is
inherently enabling of the other and so
for forest love is that which enables
choice that choice in his view you know
is and in mind to really is is
fundamental at least to the lives of
human beings we could speak about it
metaphysically perhaps not that it you
know he he has choice change and
causation at the same level together but
choices involved inherently involved and
so to enable choices to basically grant
the dignity to another to realize and
walk their own path you know even as we
are inherently in relationship with each
other
on our many varied paths and sacredness
would be I think that reality we
participate in that enables our paths to
cohere together and be in relationship
to the whole fundamentally which to me
as a whole making because the paths are
always to be walked and we are in
relationship with potential or novelty
and so the whole is something that's
dynamically changing and we are involved
in the choices we make to enable or not
that whole making so yeah meaning love
the sacred that's like a pretty simple
beautiful concepts I hope some of that
landed in interesting ways yeah
definitely do you think we've done a
disservice in modern English by
combining the different types of love to
one word where as opposed to a gap in
philia and eros I mean it's pretty
remarkable we have language it's all I
mean it's it's it's like every day
something gets revealed to me in
conversation with someone where people
take a word I was talking to a guy
yesterday and we were playing a game
called the glass bead game which I tell
you about a little bit if you like and
he we were talking about the
relationship between masters and slaves
and he was using a metaphor of a of a
boat and he you know kind of just an
improvised state of being he made the
link between you know masters are able
to sort of raise their mast and sail
away to play other games and I'd never
even thought about the word mast as in
ship you know the part of a ship being
part of the word master before and I was
just like man that's so that's so
awesome and these words always nested
inside each other like no we're just put
those together or sorry you have now and
here it's like stuff like that just
blows my mind all the time you know it's
a bit you know kind of like cereal box
wordplay etymology in some sense but
then another level I'm like man these
things are so interested how we've
retained the clues there and the
meanings there so yeah for sure there's
different kinds of love but then I also
think that because we enact these
different kinds of love all the time I
mean to the extent we are in right
relationship with each other then it's
not as though I'm not convinced meanings
are lost from us and of course when
someone comes along and you know
partitions up or tells us about
different senses of a word we like oh
yeah that's that thing and that's that
thing and that's that thing and so the
language is very helpful for that and it
can open up pathways of expression but
you know my parents for instance you
know couldn't tell you about the Greek
words for love but when I was a young
child
they certainly treated me with one kind
of love and not another and so in that
sense how much have we forgotten in one
sense a lot but then in another sense
not much I'm not trying to make much of
a point here it just comes to me that I
am quite interested in how we can open
ourselves to things we're already doing
and practices we engage in which in some
sense have many of the answers we are
already looking for but yeah I mean for
sure we are fairly blunt instruments in
many ways and there's a lot more
complexity than we often speak to this
one that's one more question before I
move to questions from the from the
members so see described yourself as
being interested in the art of
transformation so what is the art of
transformation what makes it an art and
transforming into what well the
transformation is ongoing in some sense
well in you know genuine no real sense
and where is it going would speak to the
question in some sense of teleology
which you touched on before we got into
this chat but you know it's kind of
funny the things we write about
ourselves when we do little BIOS I
absolutely hate them I truly
hate them and I I the only reason I put
anything at all is because I feel like I
have to and I do want to engage with
people and I'm quite serious about the
project and all of this so I want to
kind of share you know see sort of ideas
about myself but that ultimately attract
people to collaborate with me engage
with me who might be interested in
similar things so definite pinch of salt
hey but the art of transformation well
when it comes to art we're not trying to
create something final and correct
and absolutely certain exactly there's a
sense in which it's a continued pursuit
of beauty in one way you know that I
don't think I can quite speak to that
the wonder of art exhaustively but
basically what do I mean by it I'm quite
interested very much committed to living
in a way that's less then I could
but said in a way that was trying to you
know sound smart in some sense to live
in a beautiful way to enter into
beautiful relationships to build
beautiful things and we are always
transforming you know life is
transforming in my own writing these
things are sort of nested in sided
domain which I personally reference as
loving transformation I just can't make
sense of how game making a tool can
occur without that which is able to both
sort of affirm a game and also let it go
and recreate so to have faith in some
sense of the continuity of worthwhile
being through losses or through death or
through transformation itself which you
know involves cycles of death from from
some perhaps maybe not so metaphorical
perspective you know we build things and
have to let them go we build
relationships and they serve us to a
certain point in time and unless we
unless that relationship transforms it
could be something detrimental to the
flourishing of both individuals for
example so how to change how to develop
appropriately how to enter into more
loving
relationships be more available to write
action in the world it means all of that
kind of thing to me we've been we talk a
lot about transformation here and we've
been playing with trying to insert some
symbols and ritual and I think we
tentatively come up with the concept of
the role of aspirant which is you know
where it would be more than just
becoming a member here you would sort of
declare yourself an aspirant declare
yourself that you're looking seeking to
transform your you aspire to transform
you aspire to you know engage in this
ecology of practices and and to to take
part in this in this process so yeah
that's beautiful yeah but we we have to
I mean I it's kind of funny you know I
don't know if you guys have I have this
experience where you might be asking
yourself to do something or committing
yourself to do something but until it
arrives at a certain place of expression
I just keep the idea in my mind say
alright I'm not gonna have another
cookie today but I don't properly even
perform it with with thought in a way or
it gets like it reaches a stay in
consciousness where I I could just it's
right there to be said and it's helpful
if I say it but I find that that voice
can exist with the same kind of force
and meaning just inside consciousness
but there's somewhere before it gets to
that where I'm aware of it but I haven't
quite committed to it and unless I do
you know the chances are I'm gonna have
another cookie so you know we have to
kind of commit to things and in making
those commitments to each other I think
I've heard John speak about in making
commitments to each other we're afforded
the opportunity to come to know
ourselves a bit more definitely seems to
be the case I'd like to move to
questions from the from the members so
strewing you have a question yeah hi Tim
hello
so I was wondering since you recently
interviewed Anderson Todd I was
wondering whether you might have seen
the conversation Anderson had with John
tvoaqui where he suggested to join that
alchemy was approached to a cognitive
science if you have do you have any
thoughts to share on them yeah um I did
listen I think I probably listened a few
times
I'll be honest with you I'm not entirely
sure what science is I my sense of
science is that even when we choose
between scientific theories for their
accuracy or for their validity or their
strength or plausibility even I mean
even those things in just me trying to
reference that concept we have these
different markers of what constitutes
good science so people talk about
measure ability and repeatability as
being you know fundamental and that
seems to me like a good philosophy of
science but you know people also talk
about elegance and then they talk about
you know sort of predictive validity and
if something can be falsified and you
know how well can it be observed and
properly measured and well I guess I
would be I would I would be more sort of
and say interested because I'm
interested to talk to you about it but I
would sort of like to invite you know
Anderson to expand on what he sort of
takes science to be now I said it's a
proto cognitive science so that is kind
of limiting the claim proto being like
sort of some kind of stage before not
yet sort of fully formed but kind of
heading in that direction it's kind of
like the the building blocks well I
suppose if I can clarify that's likely
what I'm when I say protocol native
science what I'm trying to say is do you
believe it is validity towards the claim
that within alchemical texts there's
genuine information with respect to our
psychological States and how to actually
manipulate
yeah yeah I do think that I think that
we can come to increasing awareness of
what is present in consciousness and
where our attention is being drawn so
you know what is salient to us what is
populating our salient landscape am i
you know it's interesting I have to sort
of take myself into quite a lived place
to begin to talk about this sort of
stuff because what is great correct me
if I'm wrong but what's kind of really
being asked is for us to step into a
state of consciousness where we are
present with kind of potentially very
volatile states of consciousness so a
stage in that our chemical process would
be I mean god they have the they have
the the the fire so what's that cow I
forget that if you get the word I think
it's the calcination calcination yeah so
they have the calcination I have
sublimation they have dissolution they
have the reco AG Y elation so that so
that so the kind of letting go the
differentiating the dissolving and the
building back up and various ways of
entering these kind of states so the
other day it was about 11 a.m.
uh sorry 11 p.m. and I felt as though I
needed to move quite a bit of energy so
I smoked quite a lot of weed and I don't
often do that but I do do it when I feel
like I could benefit from bending some
quite intense time
moving energy and what that feels like
is basically an array of visionary type
experience where all the while identity
itself is sort of shifting so it's not
clear exactly where I am I should be
holding my ground so you want to be
quite careful about your your safety in
some sense with that you've got to have
a it helps to have a capacity to really
tune in and check in with the breath and
be in touch with one's body to be safe
but it's a kind of helpful process for
surfacing narratives ideas fragments of
relationships with people commitments
you've made things you haven't done
things you've been pushing away things
you've forgotten and there's so much
material that is sort of being broken up
and presented and well what do we make
of that how do we how do we orient in
that space what is what does it become
appropriate then to congeal together
right finding continuity in that Who am
I in how do I like for example in
constructing this sentence right now I
mean because I'm not that good at doing
this I try to be better but maybe what
I'm saying is not that interesting to
some people some people are kind of not
following this thing it's not making
sense but maybe there's a few people
where it's like are there something
there you're trying to speak to and I'm
kind of getting it and it's kind of
interesting well what is that process
what is that process like we're on some
it's like we're tending to a channel of
communication what are we tending to it
for well we're trying to seek and
understand things I mean we have a broad
sense of the game we're playing somehow
and that games nested in other games for
me want to sort of develop ourselves
such as to play more appropriately
within a particular game perhaps
transform it so it might come into a
better relationship with other games
like you know these things we'll come
back to what do we care about at all and
that's probably a question of identity
like Who am I
what is mine to do these that being
temporally bounded in some sense but
then in another sense how do we engage
in a process which enables us to change
artfully in a kind of continuity
relationship with a set of values or
virtues which essentially consists in
that which enables us to continue to
play and remake games so so does alchemy
offer a kind of toolkit for mapping or
characterizing how we can come to know
ourselves engage in the processes of
transformation within he described it to
me as cooking with being Anderson did
and he also described alchemy in fact as
the art of transformation with that very
very much in my opinion the
Philosopher's Stone can be thought of as
a symbol for self-organizing criticality
in that that's Wayne and I generally
approach it but everything else that you
said ties in a lot with that I think you
know the the process of what is a layer
to gold right you know that that's
virtual if you take an N transform it in
a spiritual sense and yes it does very
much speak to a personal transformation
where you're trying to bring the
elements together in order to make a
great work yes I mean yes and then what
are those so we bring those elements
together so that philosopher's stone is
a self-organizing criticality the self
making criticality but then so
fascinatingly like that the distinction
between the internal and the external is
also blurred in this way of thinking and
certainly from a perspective of process
velocity its philosophy and the kind of
an or the Union depth psychological
approach we have this you know the
council within the system within and
then the system without the council
without so this self-organizing
criticality to me this
this is properly seen as also in
relationship with the self-organizing
criticality z' of other people which
themselves coagulate and differentiate
and integrate into systems which
demonstrate the same kind of self making
like have to demonstrate the same kind
of self making behavior at least insofar
as it enables any of things any of this
to continue so self how can we be self
making together can you clarify what a
self-organizing critical criticality is
well John spoke about that during key is
awaking from the meeting crisis the
lecture series in nature things are
self-organizing which means
fundamentally that like a tornado
self-organizing that the the processes
that lead towards a tornado will
reinforce the tornados existence so
it'll spin faster and faster and faster
until it gets to a point where
eventually entropy takes over in the
entire system collapses natural systems
follow that process very much where they
and living systems especially follow
that and I've this research to show that
the brain actively seeks our
self-organizing criticality where
information the theory is that
information processing maximizes on the
on the line that is the border between
order and chaos and so what the
Philosopher's Stone here we would be
signifying it is the border that's on
the on the line between order and chaos
sorry the line that's on the border
between order and chaos and then so the
way that I look at it from an alchemy
perspective is it that the Philosopher's
Stone you're supposed to get the
philosopher's stone but the the
Philosopher's Stone isn't the end it's
the means and then so like the
Philosopher's Stone is understanding
self-organizing criticality but then
you've got to take that understanding
and apply it to the world and understand
that there's all these other
self-organizing criticality which you
have to interface with and so that to me
is like what the what the whole
alchemists association with
self-organizing criticality would be in
terms of trying to get the two languages
to speak together the scientific and the
psychological let's say
yeah I think that's a nice articulation
I have thought a few times in response
to John speaking about this
self-organizing criticality
I can't remember exactly but I thought
he differentiated between the
self-organizing and the self making in
some sense so that a tornado doesn't
seek how the conditions of its own
making yeah yeah the living system has a
governor which which which which seeks
out to reinforce the self-organizing
criticality and the tornado would lack
that so it has yeah it's only while the
environment enforces the the
self-organizing criticality is the
tornado continues to spin but the living
organism has something above that
because it actually actively tries to
prevent what or tries to intercede
against environmental patterns which
would disrupt the the self-organizing
criticality and I think John argues that
parasitic processing is largely a result
of the self-organizing criticality
attempting to keep the environment at
bay in this way hmm yeah that's very
very helpful so a key a key
differentiating feature then to use some
of the language that I've just brought
in in this conversation would be the
self making process is actually capable
of creating new games it could be a
degree with that yeah and that would
sort of take me to where like mostly
where I'm at at the moment is how can we
make new games together yeah well I
would say that that's the 11 the
creativity and the ability to make
choices that that's where it all comes
from right yeah yeah yeah exactly so we
have to kind there's a kind of like a
baseline what's the minimal viable but
neces what other kind of necessary I
mean to speak of sufficiency is also to
speak of kind of like if we actually
have the actuation potential to get up
off our backsides and be able to do
anything it also may be sufficient
there's another couple things but what
are kind of the core necessary features
of what
characterizes the right relationship of
coming into like building games with
other players so dignifying the the
player like capacity and others so
there's a kind of dignity there and it
got to be an integrity of the
communication channel and then there's a
kind of directionality as far as I can
tell which I think of something like
forest talks about life lived well and
fully and it's just obviously could mean
a lot of different things by that but a
kind of a directionality of a kind of a
flourishing development although the
word flourishing I sometimes tend to
stay away from but that's probably just
due to city bias reasons and sometimes
frustration with sam Harris a little bit
even though I do respect him as a person
um but yeah how do we what are kind of
the minimal viable virtues axioms that
enable the right relationship of game
making together seems to be a very ripe
inquiry than what you think about that I
think that that sounded to me just like
the application form to the religion
it's not a religion section of the
server it sounds like you've got to say
and I think that you should not to be
part of that conversation because yeah
that that's basically what we're all
interested in as well yeah awesome yeah
yeah cool well I mean yeah so I I would
like to be part of that conversation we
can talk about we can talk about that
afterwards if you like it would sort of
come down a little bit to a kind of well
actually a rational structuring of all
of our energies fundamentally which
would be to engage in the discussion a
lot of it is where to engage in the
discussion and I'm also trying to think
yeah well we've designed documents and
kind of everything at the moment so I
mean yeah those questions are exactly
the right questions I think yeah yeah
beautiful all right then well we can we
can pick this back up we can pick this
back up yeah Tim I'm not sure if it's
just me but I'm not seeing your video
maybe you could click it on and off or
is it just me can other people saw your
video
I think I'm fine so maybe it's just me a
little choppy I can say it might just be
you and I can't see
all right so some of us my video is
definitely alright okay that's it I'll
try turning it off and on let's have a
look sure see if oh yeah I can see you
now
great all right Lord dr. doom you have
hopefully not - doom full question
whoo-hoo maybe I should have come up
with a tuneful one no I I just wanted to
ask you in your study of philosophy
what's your favorite existential idea
from a playful perspective like an
integrating into the beam mode and then
the same question but for John's work so
what's your favorite existential idea in
general and what's your favorite
existential idea from John's work mmm
favorite existential idea so an example
would be like agape or it's like you get
into the loving state where you afford
the other that's a possibility and
growth in a positive direction like that
would be an existential idea all right
well then non John's work one so Sartre
said existence precedes essence meaning
that we have to make our meaning
fundamentally right there's not anything
like prescribed in our beingness itself
which is it's like there for us already
and I this is not one of my favorite
ideas I don't I don't agree with this
precisely but it's playful
because I remember just consistently
thinking about this our existence
precedes essence over the essence
precedes existence how do we but the the
the playfulness is in the the the the
kind of act of
being itself and we seem to we take in
perception and then we spin it around
and we come out with expression and
we're consistently undergoing this
process and so it's a kind of rejection
of the fixed frame of reference as being
able to appropriately characterize
meaning at all so such it would be about
then you know how do we respond to this
thrown us that we find ourselves in kind
of unmoored from a proscribed meaning in
life and we have to go out and kind of
make it I mean it's been a while since
I've read this stuff I'm probably
butchering it but but actually our
capacity to make you know what I mean
our capacity to make and to show up and
to engage in anything at all is
indicative of a capacity to do just that
and it's never been anything but that
but that is not a reduction of it away
it's contemplating it from a different
set of axioms that is much more fluent
with a process type thinking and
understanding ourselves as embedded
relations within imbedded relations that
are nevertheless influential on that
flow so we're involved in our
meaning-making and that is a real
relationship you know in the world
but it's a real relationship with the
world so in terms of John's work in
terms of existential ideas of John's
work it's hard because there's so much
of the architecture of his teaching that
has been so influential on me I wouldn't
know exactly where to pick out one
particular thing
it's what I'm about to say is altogether
too sweet but what what John embodies
and enacts in his way of dialoguing with
people is exemplary of a kind of more
than an existential idea because it's
it's not just an idea and obviously
proposition of space it's a way of
coming into relation with people which
is you know he has a lot to teach and
it's appropriate that we listen to him
if we want to learn about things he's
learned about obviously because we don't
have that learning necessarily and then
once we do have it we can talk about
other things but he has a way of I think
opening up dialogue and being receptive
to other perspectives while teaching
framing the conversation teaching and
also maneuvering it in a way that I
think is very positive
as far as interaction on the public
stage goes and that seems to me like a
very existentially important thing what
would be the existential idea in that
that we're all involved right
that we actually all do matter
and that we have to speak to each
other's virtues we have to we have to
resonate with each other's dignity you
know
that we are all involved in coupling
processes with reality and with each
other and that's deeply life-affirming
to me you know there's other ways to get
at these ideas I don't think precisely
that sense is you know I don't think I
think I learned that from John but I
think his exemplification of that in
dialog is deeply important given the
lack of
that in much public discussion around
topics as important as you know God
sacredness and the meaning of life I
hope that wasn't a cop-out question I'm
not good at picking out particular ideas
located that was brilliant thank you
yeah I'm gonna skip ahead a bit because
I know Lorene has uh has her own meeting
starting in a few minutes with authentic
relating games Loreen you had a question
hi Thank You Brett my team it's good to
see you also here in the I've joined him
in voice after crafting so so what I
wanted to ask is that what do you think
is there this role of games when it
comes to the art of transformation so
what is this game design or if you can
say that in a metaphor what does that
look like well if we put a tiny child
out in a professional rugby pitch that
child is not going to have a good time
and even though ostensibly that child's
being put out in a game he's not really
playing that game right it's just gonna
get trampled and it's not going to learn
and it's going to be all together a
tragic thing so we learn through playing
games ie I think those environments
where the curious playful spirit is
actually able to explore and then
receive feedback in a way that doesn't
end all possibility of further feedback
right like how can we come to understand
what is in our zone of agency unless we
come up to the edge of where that is you
know like when you're bundling or
wrestling you know with a with a sibling
or your parents when you're really young
kind of figuring out what it's
appropriate to touch and how hard to
pull and all the rest of it and through
that process you come to an
understanding of what the others like
but
also what effects you have and it's not
an actual fight to the death which means
that the process of learning can
continue so the importance of making
games is is critical because games are
the environments where we get to test
ourselves extend ourselves play and yeah
I mean it's got to be something a bit
more interesting I can add to that was
where serious play comes in yeah yeah
serious play for sure I mean it's got to
you know the serious serious players is
I suppose how how enabled so you've got
to have so the serious play is obviously
taking place in a setting right so it's
it's these things have to happen all at
once which is kind of why I'm struggling
to talk about it right now because we're
talking about making games and playing
games well and we have to play our way
to making the games but we are doing
something that's quite different from
ordinary game playing that's already
been set out because what we're doing is
looking to push the boundaries of a
whole set of different games
interactions styles like maybe I could
give an example of how I'm thinking
about what kind of games I would like to
see played in a way that invited
actually viewing of them in a fashion
that we currently have so not that I
want to continue this spectacle of kind
of passive absorption of information
without a deeper kind of participatory
sense of mattering to that process but
what we see for example in the game of
politics is a whole bunch of pretence on
the outside
and then kind of inner workings on the
inside where the real games are being
played regarding the manipulation of
power and who's getting what and how to
balance my resources fundamentally
within games that we're not telling you
about so there's a kind of we're on the
outside of a bunch of games but we're
playing a game through voting and
through like not rebelling and only
rioting so much or accepting more or
less the prescriptions that come down to
us but there's a disconnect in
authenticity there's a disconnect in our
trust of the right relationship between
all of these things so I'm kind of
interested in creating a space that you
know a bit like a bit like this in that
you know the questions being asked are
real serious deep questions and either I
have something interesting to say about
it or I don't and that whole process is
going to be played out right before you
so the kind of games I'm interested to
see are ones where the absolute fullness
of the perceptual matrix of self of a
particular individual which is a term
from Forrest Landry's work the absolute
fullness of an individual's perception
can be cooled it can be cooled upon and
offered in relationship in a particular
game space
so in some sense anything I have to give
that's valuable I can offer it but
what's required in order for that
offering to be what's required in order
for it be set to be safe enough for me
to offer that in some sense it's still
going to be a risk but you know
ultimately we're offering things like
the commitment of our person you knows
where this aspirin
you know making a commitment to being
here and showing up in a certain way
basically these are games to play it's a
commitment to game making over a long
period of time at the kind of games I'm
interested to see where we where we have
people entering into covenants with one
another
covenants together where we are
committing to offer the fullness of what
we can given the integrity of
relationship is maintained such that our
giving continues to be appropriate this
is all quite abstract it's it's such
it's such a difficult one because we're
making the games at the same time as
playing them well whatever they're not
Carter one of the things we're really
interested on this forum is the creation
of new series play games of new rituals
you know to go along with the religion
that's not a religion or the wakening
from the meeting crisis and and we're
gonna be forming a committee soon to
really you know start really continue
working on these because we we've
already started so so your input would
would certainly be very welcome there as
we continue to experiment in this have
you heard of the gossiping only because
somebody posted about it on the for yeah
yeah LCC yeah so the person who posted
about that I've played a few glass bead
games with them and we sort of we've
committed to do so regularly and I find
them really awesome in many ways they
are akin to what is already achievable
in conversation itself but they provide
a bit of structure so the idea with the
glass speed gamers LCC has created it is
that you can take either one two three
or five minute turns or longer turns you
decide
begin with one where for a minute one
essentially under got liked as of a
verbal contemplation relating to a
particular theme or bead and he's come
up with a bunch so one might be game one
might be the gift one might be love
right there's a and there's a chosen in
particular ways and we sort of trade
back and forth a flow of extemporaneous
contemplation about that particular
concept and the idea is to merge with
the expression of the other not deny
one's own critical reflexive
reflectivities of it but to really
deeply listen to it and then take on
those themes and build them into one's
own expression and explore these
concepts so this is a kind of practice
that I personally find really
interesting and might be something worth
looking into
yeah there's a website for it as well
glass bead game I don't know if it's
glass bead game calm but I can link it
to the link it to the channel oh great
and yeah I did see in the share your
content channel I believe I believe it's
there yes post about that thank you for
that mark you have a question take em
I've been looking into the creation that
I think over the years around
transformation and so there's a couple
of problems tied up in my opinion with
using transformation as you sort I think
you sort of alluded to this earlier when
talking about it there we seem to be
using one word for a bunch of different
methods or strategies or events
that we refer to its transformation so
what might be just the transformation
over time and you know you could say
look if you do nothing entropy if you do
something risk right and that that's
that's non-negotiable but the most
interesting form of transformation for
what I'm trying to explore are these
so-called transformative experiences and
they can happen a number of ways and one
of the things I've been sort of asking
John about is you know in meditation you
can you can hit these transformative
experiences within the meditation that
cause sort of these second-order effects
that people notice right but they don't
necessarily integrate back into your
life and I think the same is true with
with taking psychedelics you take a
psychedelic have a good trip have a
transformative trip and yet they're the
same person afterwards except for the
reference to that one time they had the
transformative experience and so there's
two problems wrapped up here one is well
what what do we actually call that right
because it seems like we need three or
four words for different types of
transformation but and and you know if
you have a comment on that that's great
and if you don't that's fine too because
I think it's a hard thing to sort of
suss out but more importantly you know
what do we do with the transformation
that we have especially the sudden or I
don't want to say sudden the the grand
transformations right those
transformations where where you're
touching the ineffable right where you
see you have a site or an experience of
the divine
and-and-and and then how do you
integrate that like what what do you
need to do because I think this is the
right conception although I'm totally
prepared to be wrong I think you need to
cede the ground so that when and if that
happens it integrates and changes you
because it's not just about the quote
transformation it's about the
transformations effect through time into
the current time because that there
seems to be a difference there and again
maybe this is wrapped up in the
it's just like no I had any temporal
experience right that it doesn't it
doesn't go outside the window and and
these other things that I'm talking
about are actually sort of
transformative right where they've
changed me in some sense so I just
wanted to get your feel for that because
I think that you might actually have a
lot of a lot to say on that that would
be helpful to me yeah yeah I mean
awesome questions I do have a lot to say
on it I mean I just like to preface this
everyone listening I'm sorry if this is
not that coherent but I do think I can
say some things I mean sort of what
you're referencing is very relevant to
everything we've discussed so far and it
speaks to this relationship between the
player and the game
you know you can have a you can take a
win you can look through a window you
can feel a different way of being in the
world for a short space of time and come
back as it were to ordinary life and all
the conditions that you are functioning
in before are basically the same the
games that you find yourself in all
those stimulus-response relationships
you know the shared landscape of
expectation that you shared with all
your social relations and that you'd
build into your own environment the way
your objects in your house are arranged
the activities you're doing at work you
travel back and forth all these patterns
of behavior remain exactly the same and
those patterns of behavior are obviously
I mean that is ones you have to be you
be your way there right you you make
them real again when you go and undergo
those patterns now there might be a real
sense of dissonance one has when one
returns to the life one had before given
this other experience one had seen one I
like peeked behind the veil so to speak
and maybe contemplated and saw into the
arbitrariness of ways people were living
patterns of action people were engaging
in
and what do you do with that what do you
do with that is the question well the
issue is that we of course social
creatures you know Jordan who likes to
say with the expression we're obligate
tribal and when we're talking about this
transformation through you know the
alchemical part of this conversation
coming into self making or
self-organizing criticality within well
we're engaged in those processes without
as well and if the environment doesn't
continue to afford an integration of
that way of seeing into the
relationality you have with yourself and
those around you and the environment
itself well then there's just
straight-up dissonance there and it's
it's it's pretty clear that lots of
people have experiences which if they
could have them in communities and
embedded in in environments which
enabled their continued integration of
some of that experience would help to
embed that microcosm of transformative
moment you know you're talking about
into healthier macrocosm and that's you
know that's not to say anything unique
at all right like it's integration
considered over time given we're social
creatures always in relationship as well
more than social we're ecological
creatures right we're deeply involved in
in the world around us so the challenge
we have is to and of course this is
something as community is is vectoring
towards doing and it's doing right now
it's like how can we create the
environments the games as well that we
can begin to work with some of the
experiences we have some of the ways of
feeling and being we realized as
possible in certain peak States how can
we bring them into relationship such
that they are what's seen valued heard
but but ultimately
enter into a kind of a reciprocal
construction type relationship with with
the world so you know it's all well and
good to have a kind of non-dual type
experience of seeing the seeing in and
out through everything but if one comes
back to you know a screaming household
where the state of play had been to
basically just project onto one another
all the various inner maladies and
frustrations with life one had had you
know not least of which are due to a
sick game that we're all nested inside
of or sick games were nested inside of
then there's going to be bloody
dissonance isn't it's not it's gonna be
bloody easy so you know the trick is to
fundamentally create if you have no
option well if you have no option that's
almost like a strange thing to say
because I think fundamentally we
actually do always have an option but
say we've got at least the capacity to
carve out a little bit of space and time
for ourselves to be in such that we can
begin to express in a way that channeled
that perception we had that being we
were able to take part in and realize
ourselves as living if we can channel
that into expression that is seeking a
kind of a relay is a key way the word
humility is coming to me how can we both
with courage and care for the process
and those things together kind of
minuite it's no point being courageous
if you don't have a humility because
you're just gonna charge off and get
yourself done in immediately so like
what do I actually have to give here
what can I manage to do where's my zone
of proximal development where's that
risk I can take that's appropriate but a
caring for that process obviously over a
longer period of time how can I begin to
express and create for myself
an outlet and a relationship with
something that I've manifested into the
world which is like my own little portal
through which to begin to enter into
some kind of relationship of coherence
with not to objectify the thing but to
get some of that inner counsel having an
opportunity to express themselves
through a a channeled like because we
take all this content all this maelstrom
of content and possibility and somehow
right now on the tip of my tongue these
next words there's a it's coming out in
some way and of course like what am I'm
referencing a lot and it might not be
clear but there's a sense in which
there's an honest attempt to channel it
in a way that's coherent in a way that
allows a certain amount of clear light
to transmit and then we can all partake
in that light together and we can go
back and forth so to create the medium
of excommunication in one's own domain
to whatever degree one can but then
we've got to seek those relationships
with other people and it's a project
over a long periods of time you know if
you find yourself isolated when they
when things happen and to be honest with
you I've met lots of people who have
profound experiences particularly with
psychedelics without practices to
integrate them with and by the way going
back to the mat and meditating is going
to be a way to integrate these things on
a continued basis as well I'm not saying
everything has but the outwardness of
expression I personally think is quite
important but you know I meet a lot of
people who take psychedelics and have
very powerful experiences and it doesn't
seem to do them any good apart from to
hit them with a massive dose of deep
dissatisfaction with everyone around
them because they just can't find a way
to express themselves in a way that is
truly heard and that enters into a
loving construction constructive
relationship with someone else it's not
any easy thing to do to speak about a
lot of this stuff given I mean as you
were saying we don't have their words to
describe a lot of the cannot only the
content we experience but fundamentally
the it's like a reorientation in
of mind you know we we go from thinking
about it depends how seriously we take
this whole cognitive grammar thing right
at John John's always talking about how
seriously we take the cognitive grammar
that structures the flow of our
expression fundamentally but it
structures it because it's also a
perceptual lens through which we filter
it's part of that thing which filters
perception through to expression so it's
it's it's a kind of can be parasitic in
that trance jacksie of space so we are
creating the protocols and processes
communities relationality x' games
together where we can build together
languages practices that enable the
continued integration of some profoundly
different states we can realize which
seem ultimately to be clustered around
the deeper senses of connectedness we
can feel within and without and
ultimately grounded in a kind of
appreciation for the opportunity of life
itself given the absurdity of the of the
void you know that that there is
something and it can be lived right that
there that we can live at all given the
kind of void of non-being
which can be experienced in contrast
it's just like an agonizing agonizing
thing it's like man it's such a
beautiful thing we can live and but but
but - but to then speak about how it is
we can live over long periods of time
given how powerful we are as a
technological civilization now given the
kind of evolutionary grammar and
functioning we've hardwired into
ourselves over thousands and thousands
of years of death it's like man
that's a big it's a big deal to turn all
that stuff around so where is it comes
it really comes back I can't you know
being here talking to each other is
demonstrative of you know an honest
attempt to engage in a kind of
collaborative inquiry a conversation
which hopefully can spark to that which
we've experienced and those aspects of
ourselves which are seeking to meet in a
ground or in a space where they have
time to be valued and that can even be
perceived at all we are to find find the
people who are ready of their own
sovereign discernment to create with and
build with together and hold each other
in integrity throughout that whole
process so yeah I think that's hopefully
a bit of an answer yeah actually I found
that very helpful you touched upon a
bunch of themes and I think I think I
think really the big answer I got out of
that was it the informative experiences
where you're in touch with the ineffable
we should just call those profound
experiences and solve that problem that
way and then we should deal with why
we're engaging in profound experiences
that were unable to I want to say take
back with us from that place back into
the place where we are and so that would
be the problem this creates a bunch of
new problems of course but that's okay
this is why we're here thank you very
much for that that wasn't quite helpful
thank you for the question you've truly
amazed a gift questions a gifts a like I
actually feel a bit you know I'm I'm
very much glad to be here and and and
speak with you all but I I don't believe
I have anything to say that we can't say
better together
I know that's what we're kind of doing
in this format you know and and it's
it's it's an honor really to be able to
answer questions it's a beautiful
exercise for me but I you know it's not
you know and there is such such thing as
structure right you know there's three
people in this chat now and so it's you
know if everybody was to talk we have to
arrange right basically to do this over
like six hours you know so there is
there is something to be said for that
but genuinely I know how much people who
are interested in this stuff have to
offer yeah I really do
so I'm just I'm grateful to have the
opportunity to talk and so we're
grateful to have you I just have a
couple last question are you good on
time I know we're a little longer than
we absolutely no no I I can I'm here I'm
oh good so hate him oh good
yeah go ahead I I've listened to a fewer
conversations and I'm listening to live
um no home appreciate it
I yeah man thank you wealthy of course
and so I guess the most direct question
I could ask and one that may be a little
more productive in terms of generating
too pragmatic stuff to discuss is what
what can we do together what can we
collaborate on all right what what is it
that we can do in this space with not
just with our words but what is it then
we construct virtually here that will
lead us to perhaps even adjusting the
physical places in which we live that
will bind us together not just in
despair in distant words but also in
close and proximal loving relation right
like this is I'm interested in too so
yeah it didn't has your mind touched on
any of that stuff have you haven't what
is it that we could do to get in them I
mean every every day um because
this stuff there's always been grounded
for me and how can I actually
like create something valuable in ours
which becomes co-create something
valuable enough that can actually
sustain me to continue to do things and
to continue so yeah I mean it'sit's the
question um so here I kind of feel drawn
to say some things that I hope we can
you know ask for some a bit of charity
regarding because I've been thinking
about what it is to sort of build
community and how I can do that
ethically and what kinds of things I
want to build and where they're gonna
take place for a long time and I've
thought about discord and that kind of
realize is that the discord environment
is feels to me kind of kind of bit
saturated you know there's the portal
there's this discord there's the rebel
wisdom one and I realized that in my own
work my own self I haven't been able to
create something that's a strong enough
attractor to have a kind of organic
let's say community develop around the
kinds of things I was doing so then I
have to make a decision about well what
stuff can I kind of drive myself or what
communities can I involve myself in and
over the last few months I've been
building a website called voice craft
collective calm and that is a network
that you can join and it's got its built
our mighty networks so you can create
groups in there and private group secret
groups that it's basically like a social
media type channel you can you know
organize events and post articles and
share things and I'm what I'm doing is
with a big portion of my time
building relationships slowly with
people who are interesting of interested
enough to with me coordinate places in
time coordinate structures where certain
inquiry enquiries can be deepened so
there's a website called eg P dot
community the ephemeral group process my
sense is that the EDP process mixed with
developers will enable the deepening of
questions which can be tracked and
offered as gifts to other communities
and offered to the world and in the
Theotokos component offering impetus
being basically meaningful dialogue
together enabling a different kind of
working through of these themes and
concepts will enable a group of people
to say between six but maybe even up to
like 100 maybe more that have break off
into groups of maybe six and undergo
processes of inquiry which end up
extracting synthesizing rather questions
which then become further objects of
contemplate contemplation and that
process continues to deepen and then
we've gone on a four to six or eight
week journey with each other and over
the course of that time we've had a
number of conversations we've tracked a
bunch of questions and well now we see
where we are so the idea would be and
that's the idea with EGP which you can
read on the website is that these are
processes that communities local and
digital can engage in to help bring the
full complexity of cognition that they
have to offer to be able to ask better
questions
do the problem formulation better and
through that question asking you know
answers will come and maybe
collaborations of you know actuated
things in the real world happen maybe
they're about how do we solve particular
problems in the real world depending on
the group of people gathering already so
I'm kind of well I'm thinking personally
is that I basically want to attract you
know extend the invitations in a kind of
esoteric way to some number of hundred
people hundreds of people probably not
more than a few thousand to participate
in a network where different enquiries
have gone on that might that also bring
in there might be in response to kind of
conversations had by people that are
already gathering attention in the space
so you know John guy or you know that
plenty of people that seek to deepen the
inquiry and then also understand well
who can really add a lot of value to
this discussion and how can we bring
them in how can we something I call the
sacred art of invitation making how can
we invite people to participate with us
and have that invitation be evocative of
that same integrity that we commit
ourselves to holding in that dialogue in
that space in this space together now
how can we create invitations that
resonate with that sort of integrity
such that people will want to come along
and add what they can so basically how
to coordinate community inquiry and to
in those processes figure out how to and
I've got some ideas about this there's
so many there's so many aspects of this
because it's kind of like a schematic
for building a community that allows
people or for people the opportunity to
really develop their
capacity to listen to perceive and to
express and to genuinely involve
themselves in the directionality of
inquiry and then to create artifacts
through that which can be shared with
others which are helpful and maybe it's
not maybe sometimes the artifacts aren't
created that's fine
but yeah just I kind of it's it's Oh
nebula is really just a right
relationship of communication Forest
said to me that one of the fundamental
problems is that we just don't spend
enough time communicating and that
community is looking to build they need
to spend about 1/3 of the time just in
conversation
a good quality conversation and there's
just not enough time put into that often
so really it's a matter of coordinating
time and you know and then obviously
resonating in the right way so my hope
is that in sort of inviting people to
join me in the journeys of inquiry
inviting people to share their creations
for you know in the engagement with
others along that process that that is
so Nora Bateson has a term called a
mutual learning environment samatha sea
which is a beautiful term and you know
that's got to be part of it how do how
do we create these mutual amber learning
environments together so we learn as we
deepen inquiry and have that matter
because well the inquiry is directly
relevant to problems of world making
culture building building languages of
communication but then that's one part
of it there's a bunch more to say about
what I personally think is required in
the broader public media space which I
actually feel as though what I have to
say about that and I kind of want to
explore it privately or at least not non
recorded
which is kind of interesting right
almost goes against some of the things
I've been saying but the thing is that
ownership of brand of the medium or
platform that houses the kind of
conversations required I think to be
cathartic and transformative at the
level political and social in our time
given its fractured nature I don't think
I don't think that space can be owned I
don't think it can work if the
conversations are taking place in
someone's house that they own I actually
think we need to collaborate in
basically building a Burning Man type
dynamic of structure that recedes once
its event occurs and the only thing that
remains is the integrity of relationship
established among those who participated
and co-created but that the actual
structure itself there's kind of two
things like on the one hand I want to
participate with people in their own
communities in a network I'm building
but then I also recognize there's this
other thing that has to be built that
has not been built anywhere and that is
the kind of thing that I you know you
know i probe already said quite a bit
about that there so well that's awesome
you signed up for your your your
collective website there so I'm I'm
fascinated with everyone's minor
variation on the theme here that we're
all searching for and I think you know
yeah I'm deeply interested in
participating in a lot of it and I think
that we do have a chance here to to have
the serious play where we do experiment
with configurations and ways of getting
to know each
and getting into ourselves where by
maybe in the future we can avoid some of
the pitfalls that we've discovered over
the past 50 or 60 years of modernity
that in the integration of ourselves
with this technological layer and with a
hyper abundance of of all that that is
entailed by it and the differential
accumulation of those abundances let's
say in the presence of the yeah I think
all of these things are finally in a
place where at least the self-interested
and drawn can start to really address
them right so we can finally be end and
a node so yeah I don't want to lose idea
of this notion that I think the Burning
Man is key I think that is not leaveneth
the ephemeral quality of what it takes
to dynamically self-assemble into a
vehicle it has the capacities right
distributed amongst themself that
efficient mean functionally is its
representative of the same things that
we need in order to make sense at
multiple layers here in our in our
modern culture and so we need any
encourage that seems like a good idea
yeah I think you're gonna find out a lot
of a lot of overlap between your what
you're doing and what we're doing here
so anything you know that we can do to
help with that and coordinate with you
and you coordinate with us and yeah I
would love to to help bring bring these
yeah bring us together and work together
on them yeah I've got a buddy back
launching called meta gora right this is
just if each of these communities is a
city on the map I want there to be as
obvious and interstate between those
cities as there can be right we're into
that means critical yeah and and that's
really whimsical been missing is a easy
road map to navigate on the the
territory of of all the knowledge that
exists in this in the space so yeah I'm
deeply ashamed of anyone else doing that
too yeah it was just it was a bit of a
they break through but like I you know
part of the journey for me I was like
right at the beginning I could be part
of transformative conversations a bridge
making conversations but I actually
don't think at the you know in
everyone's community in everyone's
project you can aspire to those exact
same things invite people in have the
conversations share them deepen things
provide value absolutely brilliant none
of that needs to change everyone should
be doing everyone should be doing that
everyone like as much of that as
possible as a good thing but then what
you know in terms of what that
interstate is like no one can I don't
think the interstate can be just another
community that's the thing about it
because well that's just another
community then like what is it to to
actually collaborate together among
communities to create something where
there is that different space that
different plane that's what it that's
what it looks like and so you know I
mean I invite I invite the contemplation
regarding regarding that notion because
that's a that's an interesting one
sending out invitations summonings who
are fun stuff perhaps this is the space
of the shaman the modern day shop with
just attaching the notion of the
psychopomp to it there's a divestment
that has to occur with your identity
right you have to be willing to
shape-shift to to absorb to appreciate
to identify with empathize with the
presentation of whatever communal
aspects are representative of the
language that you encounter and then you
have to extrapolate from that the deeper
subterranean layers of meaning that
everyone has discovered in their
exponents perience right that represents
the truth of the language and the
culture that's developed there and then
see where that's conciliate across all
of these smaller organizations of
experience and and in the process of
doing that I think you're fundamentally
transformed into a particular shape but
kind of
my medically diverse constantly
reconfiguring you know dynamically
searching criticality I mean when you
come up with a million different ways of
mmm right this but it's fundamentally
what our brain is doing it's just this
we're we're doing this that performing
this is the cultural layer now right
that we're absorbing these old items
and attempting to make not just a
narrative but a methodology for
maneuvering through the narrative right
to place ourselves in different aspects
of it and different perspectives and
angles and find out what what may or may
not be consistent across all of it and
find the true connective tissue let's
say so yeah yeah yeah yeah it's so
interesting because it's like a
connective tissue and at the same time
it's for you know arguably it's for a
shape that has not been made that's the
thing it's like in that conversation
with Allison I recorded the last one of
my podcast it goes into a bit more in
part two about one of these ideas that
has been gripping me for so long is to
understand what the sort of a novel
archetype archetypal form would be like
can we actually make sense of that idea
because you know obviously Nietzsche had
the idea of the eternal recurrence of
the same but it's like mmm the thing
we're and people talk about feeling the
elephant I'm not I'm not talking about
feeling a elephant we haven't
you know what I mean it's might not be
an elephant so right yeah well so like
we you can think of it as like
space-filling right like if you have a
cubic volume of space what is the shape
of stuff that can be in there and then
what what can it what it can what it can
do right me so in our age we're now
we're now understanding what it is to
build up more and more complexity from
very simple structures underneath right
and a kind of heterogeneous mix of
different substances with different
capacities produces a kind of
synergistic output that that it can do
more than the sum of its parts and and
then we have a good conception of
something like metamaterials where
further and further
complexity leads to new configurations
and orientations in that volume of space
that that the material is fundamentally
capable of new properties right it can
do new entry paintings is not just
extending its prior capacities but new
and interesting things so yeah there's
yeah there that we that we can't quite
grasp yet and it is probably always the
ineffable aspect of novelty that we'll
never be able to fully contain within a
language or a writable form
but nevertheless I think we like that is
what our calling is as attentive
conscious creatures is to do the
transformational process what what the
psychopomp
is fundamentally doing is translating
from that chaotic realm of potential
what is actual what can be in what
figurations are possible with the energy
levels that were gifted so I just want
to jump jump in for a sec the
conversation can continue but I'd like
to bring the the official Q&A to a do to
a close
so I wanted to thank Tim for being here
this has been fantastic I want to thank
everybody for asking such great
questions this has been a really great
Q&A and I'm grateful to everyone for
being here today and thank you too yeah
thank you it's been a trip so thank you
everybody so we're gonna and and and the
recording but uh obviously you can stay
and talk tomorrow we've got layman
Pascal coming for a return visit so so
please come for that at 6 p.m. Eastern
Time
come back Monday we've got John back for
for a QA so thank you everybody and and
have a great night
Thank You Brett thank you Jim
take care yeah thank you